<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-30T16:24:13+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">spcg</title><subtitle>Jekyll theme for research project websites</subtitle><author><name>SPCG</name></author><entry><title type="html">Physiology of Cell Growth</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/cell-growth" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Physiology of Cell Growth" /><published>2019-01-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/cell-growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/cell-growth"><![CDATA[<p>We work on quantitative models for cell growth that describe how cells proliferate under different enviromental conditions. One of our main goals is understanding the regulatory circuits that govern cell growth and how those circuits react to perturbations such as nutrient limitations or drug treatment. We approach this question using both data-driven and model-driven methods: we make use of data provided from our experimental collaborators to build models, and we plan new experiments based on our models to test the model predictions. We are actively working on E. coli, yeast and cultured mammalian cell lines, to find common and specific traits of growth regulation.</p>

<p>Working on this topic: Rossana Droghetti, Mattia Corigliano, Giorgio Tallarico, Andrea Ripamonti</p>

<p>Key publications:</p>

<p>L Calabrese, L Ciandrini, M Cosentino Lagomarsino. How total mRNA influences cell growth. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 121 (21) 2024</p>

<p>L Calabrese, J Grilli, M Osella, CP Kempes, M Cosentino Lagomarsino, L Ciandrini. Protein degradation sets the fraction of active ribosomes at vanishing growth. PLoS Comput Biol 18(5):e1010059 2022</p>

<p>Q Zhang, E Brambilla, R Li, H Shi, M Cosentino Lagomarsino, B Sclavi A decrease in transcription capacity limits growth rate upon translation inhibition. Msystems 5 (5) 2020</p>

<p><a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=jJ0S7vUAAAAJ" title="Google Scholar" target="_blank">More on Google Scholar</a></p>]]></content><author><name>SPCG</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We work on quantitative models for cell growth that describe how cells proliferate under different enviromental conditions. One of our main goals is understanding the regulatory circuits that govern cell growth and how those circuits react to perturbations such as nutrient limitations or drug treatment. We approach this question using both data-driven and model-driven methods: we make use of data provided from our experimental collaborators to build models, and we plan new experiments based on our models to test the model predictions. We are actively working on E. coli, yeast and cultured mammalian cell lines, to find common and specific traits of growth regulation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Physiology of Cell Cycle</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/cell-cycle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Physiology of Cell Cycle" /><published>2019-01-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/cell-cycle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/cell-cycle"><![CDATA[<p>We are interested in how cells control cell-cycle progression to ensure that key processes are brought to completion. New dynamic single-cell data challenge standard views and raise new questions. Quantitative models are needed to infer the key mechanisms and guide the experiments. In E. coli, with single-cell experiments, extensive data-analysis and modeling study, we have recently reported that a concurrency between processes happening both at the chromosome and the cell level typically limit cell division with comparable odds, which vey with conditions and perturbations. In single cultured mammalian cells, we have shown that both subperiod timing adjustments and growth-rate regulation contribute to cell-cycle progression decisions. In yeast and in breast cancer cells, we are currently exploring how the extreme deviation of cell size from homeostatic values during a G1 cell-cycle arrest can affect cell proliferation after release from the arrest.</p>

<p>Working on this topic: Mattia Corigliano, Giorgio Tallarico, Valentina Guarino</p>

<p>Key publications:</p>

<p>I Iuliani, G Mbemba, M Cosentino Lagomarsino, B Sclavi. Direct single-cell observation of a key Escherichia coli cell-cycle oscillator. Science Advances 10:29 2024</p>

<p>M Panlilio, J Grilli, G Tallarico, I Iuliani, B Sclavi, P Cicuta, M Cosentino Lagomarsino, Threshold accumulation of a constitutive protein explains E. coli cell-division behavior in nutrient upshifts Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 118 (18) 2 2021</p>

<p>G Micali, J Grilli, M Osella, M Cosentino Lagomarsino, Concurrent processes set E. coli cell division Science Advances 4:11 eaau3324 2018</p>

<p><a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=jJ0S7vUAAAAJ" title="Google Scholar" target="_blank">More on Google Scholar</a></p>]]></content><author><name>SPCG</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are interested in how cells control cell-cycle progression to ensure that key processes are brought to completion. New dynamic single-cell data challenge standard views and raise new questions. Quantitative models are needed to infer the key mechanisms and guide the experiments. In E. coli, with single-cell experiments, extensive data-analysis and modeling study, we have recently reported that a concurrency between processes happening both at the chromosome and the cell level typically limit cell division with comparable odds, which vey with conditions and perturbations. In single cultured mammalian cells, we have shown that both subperiod timing adjustments and growth-rate regulation contribute to cell-cycle progression decisions. In yeast and in breast cancer cells, we are currently exploring how the extreme deviation of cell size from homeostatic values during a G1 cell-cycle arrest can affect cell proliferation after release from the arrest.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chromosome Organization</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/chrom-org" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chromosome Organization" /><published>2019-01-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/chrom-organization</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/chrom-org"><![CDATA[<p>We are interested in the physical aspects of chromosome organization and dynamics that play a relevant physiological role in the cell. We model how bridging proteins, external tension and crowding from the nucleoplasm or the bacterial cytoplasm affect chromosome organization, dynamics and propagation of mechanical stress. We are particularly interested in the role played by chromosomes in cell cycle decisions.</p>

<p>Working on this topic: Marco Cosentino Lagomarsino, Mattia Corigliano</p>

<p>Key publications:</p>

<p>M Negri, M Gherardi, G Tiana and M Cosentino Lagomarsino, Spontaneous domain formation in disordered copolymers as a mechanism for chromosome structuring, Soft Matter, 14, 6128-6136 2018</p>

<p>KE Polovnikov, M Gherardi, M Cosentino Lagomarsino, MV Tamm, Folding and cytoplasm viscoelasticity contribute jointly to chromosome dynamics Physical Review Letters 120 (8), 088101, 2018</p>

<p>A Javer, NJ Kuwada, Z Long, VG Benza, KD Dorfman, PA Wiggins, P Cicuta, M Cosentino Lagomarsino, Persistent super-diffusive motion of Escherichia coli chromosomal loci. Nature Communications 5 3854, 2014</p>

<p><a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=jJ0S7vUAAAAJ" title="Google Scholar" target="_blank">More on Google Scholar</a></p>]]></content><author><name>SPCG</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are interested in the physical aspects of chromosome organization and dynamics that play a relevant physiological role in the cell. We model how bridging proteins, external tension and crowding from the nucleoplasm or the bacterial cytoplasm affect chromosome organization, dynamics and propagation of mechanical stress. We are particularly interested in the role played by chromosomes in cell cycle decisions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quantification of Mutational Processes and Phenotypic Switches</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/mutat-phen" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quantification of Mutational Processes and Phenotypic Switches" /><published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/mutation-phenot-process</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/mutat-phen"><![CDATA[<p>We aim to quantify mutational processes and phenotypic transitions in mammalian cells and cancer model systems, combining experimental evolution and mathematical modeling. To this end, we develop quantitative frameworks inspired by the Luria-Delbrück fluctuation assay to quantify the phenotypic switch to the persister phenotype and mutation rates in cancer cells exposed to growth-inhibitory targeted therapies. Our work also includes inference methods to quantify genomic mutation rates using sequencing data from controlled experimental setups. Furthermore, we are advancing computational methods to evaluate the potential effects of natural selection in shaping the phenotypes arising during a Mutation Accumulation experiment carried out in single-celled organisms.</p>

<p>Working on this topic: Simone Pompei, Mattia Corigliano, Valentina Guarino</p>

<p>Key publications:</p>

<p>M Russo, S Pompei, A Sogari, M Corigliano, G Crisafulli, A Puliafito, S Lamba, J Erriquez, A Bertotti, M Gherardi, F Di Nicolantonio, A Bardelli, M Cosentino Lagomarsino. A modified fluctuation-test framework characterizes the population dynamics and mutation rate of colorectal cancer persister cells. Nat Genet 54(7):976-984 2022</p>

<p>M Russo, G Crisafulli, A Sogari, NM Reilly, S Arena, S Lamba, A Bartolini, V Amodio, A Magrì, L Novara, I Sarotto, ZD Nagel, CG Piett, A Amatu, A Sartore-Bianchi, S Siena, A Bertotti, L Trusolino, M Corigliano, M Gherardi, M Cosentino Lagomarsino, F Di Nicolantonio, A Bardelli. Adaptive mutability of colorectal cancers in response to targeted therapies. Science 366 6472, 1473-1480 2019</p>

<p><a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=jJ0S7vUAAAAJ" title="Google Scholar" target="_blank">More on Google Scholar</a></p>]]></content><author><name>SPCG</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We aim to quantify mutational processes and phenotypic transitions in mammalian cells and cancer model systems, combining experimental evolution and mathematical modeling. To this end, we develop quantitative frameworks inspired by the Luria-Delbrück fluctuation assay to quantify the phenotypic switch to the persister phenotype and mutation rates in cancer cells exposed to growth-inhibitory targeted therapies. Our work also includes inference methods to quantify genomic mutation rates using sequencing data from controlled experimental setups. Furthermore, we are advancing computational methods to evaluate the potential effects of natural selection in shaping the phenotypes arising during a Mutation Accumulation experiment carried out in single-celled organisms.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Evolution of Chromosomes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/chrom-evo" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evolution of Chromosomes" /><published>2019-01-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/chrom-evo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/chrom-evo"><![CDATA[<p>We work on evolutionary models that help us understand genome architecture. Our goal is to quantify the evolutionary forces that shape the structural variation of the genes and the genome, such as mutations and chromosome duplication, together with their effect on the reproductive fitness of the individuals. Recently, we have also set up a model that accounts for the aquisition and loss of DNA replication origins in Yeast.</p>

<p>Working on this topic: Simone Pompei, Rossana Droghetti</p>

<p>Key publications:</p>

<p>S Pompei, M Cosentino Lagomarsino, A fitness trade-off explains the early fate of yeast aneuploids with chromosome gains, Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 120 (15) 2023</p>

<p>R Droghetti, N Agier, G Fischer, M Gherardi, M Cosentino Lagomarsino, An evolutionary model identifies the main evolutionary biases for the evolution of genome-replication profiles. Elife 10, e63542 2021</p>

<p>M Yousuf, I Iuliani, RT Veetil, A Seshasayee, B Sclavi, M Cosentino Lagomarsino, Early fate of Exogenous promoters in E. coli, Nucleic acids research 48 (5), 2348-2356, 2020</p>

<p><a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=jJ0S7vUAAAAJ" title="Google Scholar" target="_blank">More on Google Scholar</a></p>]]></content><author><name>SPCG</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We work on evolutionary models that help us understand genome architecture. Our goal is to quantify the evolutionary forces that shape the structural variation of the genes and the genome, such as mutations and chromosome duplication, together with their effect on the reproductive fitness of the individuals. Recently, we have also set up a model that accounts for the aquisition and loss of DNA replication origins in Yeast.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Complex Systems Approach to Genomes and Ecosystems</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/complex-syst" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Complex Systems Approach to Genomes and Ecosystems" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/comp-syst</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/complex-syst"><![CDATA[<p>Many complex systems are modular. Such systems can be represented as “component systems,” i.e., sets of elementary components - for instance genomes as collection of genes belonging to different categories or ecosystems as sets of organisms belonging to different species. The underlying functional design and constraints of such component systems are not obvious a priori, and their detection is often a challenge of both scientific and practical importance, requiring a clear understanding of component statistics. We study the architectural features of genomes and ecosystems from the point of view of component statistics with two main questions in mind: (i) what does component statistic reveal about the underlying generative processes of the systems (ii) how can we distinguish statistical null features from functionally relevant ones.</p>

<p>Working on this topic: Simone Pompei, Mattia Corigliano</p>

<p>Key publications:</p>

<p>A Mazzolini, M Gherardi, M Caselle, M Cosentino Lagomarsino, M Osella, Statistics of shared components in complex component systems Physical Review X 8 (2), 021023, 2018</p>

<p>E de Lazzari, J Grilli, S Maslov, M Cosentino Lagomarsino, Family-specific scaling laws in bacterial genomes Nucleic Acids Research, 45(13):7615-7622. doi: 10.1093/nar/gkx510 2017</p>

<p>M Cosentino Lagomarsino, AL Sellerio, PD Heijning, and B Bassetti,  Universal features in the genome- level evolution of protein domains Genome Biology 10:R12  2009</p>

<p><a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=jJ0S7vUAAAAJ" title="Google Scholar" target="_blank">More on Google Scholar</a></p>]]></content><author><name>SPCG</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Many complex systems are modular. Such systems can be represented as “component systems,” i.e., sets of elementary components - for instance genomes as collection of genes belonging to different categories or ecosystems as sets of organisms belonging to different species. The underlying functional design and constraints of such component systems are not obvious a priori, and their detection is often a challenge of both scientific and practical importance, requiring a clear understanding of component statistics. We study the architectural features of genomes and ecosystems from the point of view of component statistics with two main questions in mind: (i) what does component statistic reveal about the underlying generative processes of the systems (ii) how can we distinguish statistical null features from functionally relevant ones.]]></summary></entry></feed>